A Finding Aid to the Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney Papers, 1851-1975, bulk 1888-1942, in the Archives of American Art AAA.whitgert
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1889-1949; 1959; Series 2; 6 Linear feet Boxes 3-9
  - Early Personal and Family Correspondence, 1889-1896; 2.1
    - Letters regarding Cornelius Vanderbilt, Jr.'s Engagement, 1895-1896 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Letters to Gertrude Vanderbilt on Her Engagement, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - Letters to Harry Payne Whitney on His Engagement, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Later Family Correspondence, 1896-1942; 2.2
    Correspondence found here is between Whitney and family members and dates from after her marriage until her death in 1942. Correspondents include her husband, mother, sister, children, and various nieces and nephews, primarily in the form of incoming letters, in addition to scattered drafts of outgoing letters in Whitney's hand.
    This series has been scanned in entirety.
    - Grandchildren, Nieces and Nephews, 1930s-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Vanderbilt, Alfred, 1896-1898 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1901-1903 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1914-1920 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Vanderbilt, Alice Gwynne, 1930-1935 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Vanderbilt, Catherine, circa 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Vanderbilt, Cornelius II, 1896; 1898 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Vanderbilt, Cornelius III (Neily), circa 1890s-1942 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Vanderbilt, Reginald Claypoole, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Vanderbilt Szechenyi, Gladys, 1896-1907 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Vanderbilt Szechenyi, Gladys, 1911-1916 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Vanderbilt Szechenyi, Gladys, and Szechenyi, Lasili, 1930-1934; 1924 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Vanderbilt Szechenyi, Gladys, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Vanderbilt Szechenyi, Gladys, 1936-1941 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1925-1934 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1935-1938 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Vanderbilt, Mrs. W. K., Jr. (Virginia aka Birdie), 1915-1919 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Whitney, Barbara, 1907-1921 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Whitney, Barbara Henry and Barklie Henry, 1922-1942 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Whitney, Cornelius (Sonny), 1907-circa 1918 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Whitney, Cornelius (Sonny), 1919-1941 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1906-1911 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1913-1914 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Whitney, Flora, and Roderick Tower, 1917-1927 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Whitney, Flora, 1928-1942 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Whitney, Harry Payne, 1898-1912 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Whitney, Harry Payne, 1915-1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Whitney, Harry Payne, 1919-1925 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Whitney, Harry Payne, 1926-1930 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Whitney, Helen Hay, 1908-1930 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Whitney, William C., 1896-1901 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Family Correspondence, circa 1890s-1920s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1896-1942; 2.3
    This series consists of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's personal and professional correspondence dating from 1896 to her death in 1942. Correspondence includes mostly incoming letters, in addition to some carbon copies of outgoing correspondence and scattered drafts of outgoing letters in Whitney's hand. Correspondents include friends, lovers, artists, architects, designers, art organizations, museums and galleries, relief and philanthropic organizations, writers, publishers, and others. While family letters are found primarily in Series 2.1. and Series 2.2., this series does include letters of condolence upon the deaths of William C. Whitney (received by Harry Payne Whitney), Harry Payne Whitney (including some received by Flora Whitney Miller), and Alice G. Vanderbilt.
    Correspondence concerns personal mattters; Whitney's sponsorship of artists (including Morgan Russell, Edgar McAdams, Laura McLane, and Frederick Roth); Whitney's sculpture commissions and exhibitions of sculpture; exhibitions of other artists' work held in Whitney's studio; art competitions sponsored by Whitney (such as Competition in Architecture, Sculpture and Painting, 1914-1915, and Immigrant in America Poster Contest, 1915); requests for assistance from struggling artists and other needy individuals; requests for work in modeling and casting; Whitney's war relief work, as well as her general philanthropy and art patronage; the purchase of Whitney's sculpture, Head of Spanish Peasant, by the Metropolitan Museum of Art; the publication of Whitney's novel Walking the Dusk as well as her other writing efforts; plans for the New York World's Fair; and awards and honorary degrees received by Whitney.
    Beginning in the early 1910s, material consists of more and more routine business correspondence which was received and created by several different secretaries on Whitney's behalf. Also found is a list of incoming correspondence received from 1915 to 1918, which was kept by Irene Givenwilson, one of Whitney's secretaries.
    Chronologically arranged folders marked "Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents" found toward the end of the series, contain a combination of letters on which the signature is absent or illegible, and hand-written notes and drafts in Whitney's hand to unidentified recipients.
    This series has been scanned in entirety, with the exception of cards and envelopes from condolence bouquets.
    Although initially arranged chronologically, correspondence has been rearranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or subject, in order to facilitate access. Generally correspondents from whom there are 5 or more letters have been given a named folder; all other correspondents are filed in folders marked "Miscellaneous" at the end of the appropriate letter group.
    - Alexander, Grace, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Allen, Annie (nee Winsor), 1896-1903 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Allen, Frederick H., 1932-1934; 1916 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Alley Festa, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - American Federation of Arts, 1916-1936 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - American Museum of Natural History (inc. Whitney Wing), 1923-1940 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - American Red Cross, 1941; 1917-1923 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Anderson, Hendrik Christian, 1900-1938 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Appleton, J. W., 1903-1935 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Art Alliance of America, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - A, First Names Only, 1910; 1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - A, Miscellaneous: A.-Am, circa 1900-1940s (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - A, Miscellaneous: An-Av, circa 1900-1940s (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Beach, Chester and Eleanor, 1915-1917 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Beaux, Cecilia, 1915-1917 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Bird, May, 1915-1917 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Bodley, Ronnie V. C., 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Brearley School, 1917-1920 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Brentano's, 1915-1917 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Burden, Adele, 1896-circa 1934 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - B, Miscellaneous: B.-Ba, circa 1900-1930s (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - B, Miscellaneous: Be, circa 1900-1930s (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - B, Miscellaneous: Bi-Bo, 1890s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - B, Miscellaneous: Br-Bu, circa 1900-1930s (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - C. & A. Richards, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - C., P., circa 1911-1942 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1918-1919; 1935 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Carroll, Philip, 1911-1917 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Carroll, Philip, 1930; 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Chalfin, Paul, 1942; 1911-1917 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Chamberlain, George Agnew, 1931-1941 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Chanler, Robert, 1915-1927 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Chateau de la Boulaye-Occupancy by German Forces, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Clayton, Paul, circa 1927 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Colony Club, 1915-1919 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Committee for Immigrants in America, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Competition in Architecture, Sculpture, and Painting, 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Cottonet, R. L., and F. M., 1896-1934 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Coward McCann Inc., 1932-1940 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Crocker, Frank L., 1931-1941 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Crocker, Frank L., re: Estate of Harry Payne Whitney, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Crowninshield, Frank, 1915-1920 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Curtis, Marjorie, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Cushing, Howard, 1902-circa 1912 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - C, First Names Only, circa 1920s; 1937 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - C, Miscellaneous: C.-Ca, circa 1890s-circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 53)
      Includes 2 letters from Alexander Calder
    - C, Miscellaneous: Ce-Cl, circa 1900s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - C, Miscellaneous: Co-Cu, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Davidson, Jo and Florence, circa 1919-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Delano & Aldrich, 1915-1919 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - De Strelecki, J., 1916-1919 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Draper, Charles, 1907-1939 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Duell, Charles, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - D, First Names Only, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - D, Miscellaneous: Da, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Includes letter from Arthur B. Davies
    - D, Miscellaneous: De, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - D, Miscellaneous: Dh-Do, circa 1890s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - D, Miscellaneous: Dr-Dw, circa 1890s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Earl, Maud, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Elliott, Maud Howe, 1916-1922 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Elwood, Philip H., Jr., 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - E, First Names Only, 1890s-1920s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - E, Miscellaneous, circa 1910-1920s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Fairmount Park Art Association, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Favai, Gennaro and Maria, 1915-1919 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Ferris, Hugh, 1931-1932 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Fleck, Harry T., 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Force, Juliana, circa 1911-1941 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Frazier, Julia (Mrs. Kenneth Frazier), 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - French, Daniel C., 1916; 1907 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Friends of the Young Artists, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Friends of the Young Artists, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - F, Miscellaneous, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Gerry, Mabel, 1911-1930; 1896 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Gibson, Charles, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Gillies, John Wallace, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Givenwilson, Irene, 1914-1918 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Gregory, Elizabeth, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Gregory, John, 1909-1919; 1930 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Groth, Catherine (Lee), 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Guardabassi, Francesco Mario, 1914-1942 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - G, First Names Only, 1930s-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - G, Miscellaneous: Gl-Gw, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Hammond, Emily and John Henry, 1930; 1917-1918 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Hammond, Natalie H., 1912-1918 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), 1931 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), 1932 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), circa 1934 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), 1935 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Hartwell, John A. (Josh), circa 1939-1941 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Haseltine, Herbert, 1910-1936 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Hav, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Hazard, Margaret Kellog, circa 1917-1920 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Henri, Robert, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Henry, Lucien, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Hoffman, Malvina, 1915-1917 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Hunt, Esther, 1896-1900 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Hunter College of the City of New York, 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - H, Miscellaneous: H.-Has, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - H, Miscellaneous: Hat-Hi, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - H, Miscellaneous: Ho-Hy, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Immigrant in America Poster Contest, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - I, First Names Only, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - I, Miscellaneous, 1918-1923 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - J, First Names Only, circa 1915-1930s (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - J, Miscellaneous, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - K, First Names Only, 1908-1916 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - K, Miscellaneous: K.-Ki, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - K, Miscellaneous: Kl-Ku, circa 1900-1930s (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Lanier, Harriet (Mrs. J.F.D.), 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Lincoln National Bank, 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - List of Incoming Correspondence Kept by Irene Givenwilson (Gertrude V. Whitney's secretary), 1915-1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Little Club, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Lydig, Rita (Mrs. Philip), 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - L, First Names Only, 1896-1911; 1942 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - L, Miscellaneous: La-Le, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - L, Miscellaneous: Li-Ly, circa 1900-1930s (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - M. Knoedler & Co., 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - M. Knoedler & Co., Whitney Exhibition, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Martin, Walton, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Maule, M. F., 1907 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - McAdams, Edgar, circa 1915 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - McLane, Laura, circa 1916 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1916-1941 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Minazzoli, Eddie, 1911-1932 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Moffat, John, 1917-1920 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Morgan, Laura, circa 1934-circa 1941 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - M, First Names Only, 1914-1934 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - M, Miscellaneous: Ma, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - M, Miscellaneous: Mc, circa 1900-1940 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - M, Miscellaneous: Me-Mo, 1890s-circa 1942 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - M, Miscellaneous: Mu, circa 1890s-circa 1942 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - National Arts Club, 1916-1920 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - National Sculpture Society, 1915-1929 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - New Jersey College for Women, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - New York World's Fair, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - New York World's Fair, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Newport Art Association, 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Newport Art Association, 1918-1940 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Noland, Charlotte, 1916-1920 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - N, First Names Only, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - N, Miscellaneous, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - O, First Names Only, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - O, Miscellaneous, circa 1910-1930s (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, 1915-1916 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Parrish, Maxfield, 1916-1918 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Pepper, George Wharton, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 38-39)
    - Pepper, George Wharton, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Pietro, S. C. (Friends of the Young Artists), 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Pulitzer, Mrs. Ralph, 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Purdy, W. Frank (The Gorham Co.), 1915-1919 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - P, First Names Only, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - P, Miscellaneous: Pa, circa 1910-1930s (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - P, Miscellaneous: Pe-Pf, circa 1910-1930s (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - P, Miscellaneous: Ph-Pu, circa 1910-1930s (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Q, Miscellaneous, 1931; 1922 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Ramon, Adolpho, 1915-1919 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Ramon, Rafael, circa 1911-1916 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Ranken, William, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Regan, Thos. J., 1914-1920 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Regan, Thos. J., 1931-1942 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Roth, Frederick G. R., 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Russell, Morgan, 1910-1930 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - R, Miscellaneous: Ra-Ri, circa 1910-1930s (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - R, Miscellaneous: Ro-Ru, circa 1900-1941 (Box 7, Folder 57)
      Includes a telegram from Auguste Rodin and a letters from Eleanor Roosevelt, Quentin Roosevelt and Theodore Roosevelt)
    - San Francisco Art Association, 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Sands, Robert Cornell, 1915-1930 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Sanger, Virginia (Mrs. Ralph), 1916-1920 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - School Art League, 1916-1917 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Scott & Fowles, 1930; 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Scudder, Janet, 1916-1919 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Severn, Elizabeth, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Society of Independent Artists, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Soldwedel, Frederick A., 1916-1919 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Sorchan, Charlotte (Mrs. Victor), 1917 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Stackpole, William, 1907-1930 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Stevens, Ada B., 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Stewart, Lila, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Studio, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - S, Miscellaneous: S.-Sa, circa 1900-1930s (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Includes letter from Augustus Saint-Gaudens)
    - S, Miscellaneous: Sc-Sh, circa 1910-1930s (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - S, Miscellaneous: Si-So, 1896-1930s (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Includes 2 letters from John Sloan)
    - S, Miscellaneous: Sp-Sw, circa 1900-1930s (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Tiffany & Co., 1916-1920 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Toledo Museum of Art, 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - T, First Names Only, 1917-1940 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - T, Miscellaneous, circa 1900-circa 1940s (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - U, Miscellaneous, 1917-1920 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - V, Miscellaneous, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Ward, Winifred, 1915-1917 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Warren, Lloyd, 1909-1918 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Watson, Forbes, circa 1919-1936 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Watts, Diana, 1915-1917 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Weston, Mrs. C., 1917 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Woodruff, Helen S. (Mrs. Lewis B.), 1916-1923 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - W, First Names Only (Bill/William), circa 1922-1930 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - W, Miscellaneous: W.-Wa, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - W, Miscellaneous: We-Wig, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wil-Wy, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Young, J. W., 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Y, First Names Only, 1931-circa 1934 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Y, Miscellaneous, 1915-1934 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Z, Miscellaneous, circa 1916-1939 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, circa 1900-circa 1942 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1896 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1907-1908 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, circa 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, circa 1914-1916 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1917-1920 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1920s (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, Probably inc. Paul Clayton, 1927-1928 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous/Unknown Correspondents, 1931-1941 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Letters of Condolence to Harry Payne Whitney Upon the Death of His Father (William C. Whitney), 1904 (Box 8, Folder 50-53)
    - Letters of Condolence Upon the Death of Harry Payne Whitney (Box 8)
      - Letters, A-B, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 54)
      - Letters, C-E, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 55)
      - Letters, F-H, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 56)
      - Letters, J-M, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 57)
      - Letters, N-S, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 58)
      - Letters, T-W, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 59)
      - Letters, First Names Only, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 60)
      - Letters, Illegible, Unknown, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 61)
      - List of Flowers/Letters Received, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Name Cards, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Note Cards from Condolence Bouquets, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
      - Telegrams, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Letters of Condolence to Flora Whitney Miller Upon the Death of Harry Payne Whitney (Box 9)
      - Letters, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Telegrams, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - First Names Only/Illegible, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Letters of Condolence Upon Death of Alice G. Vanderbilt (Box 9)
      - Letters, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Telegrams, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - First Names Only/Illegible, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Posthumous Correspondence, 1942-1949; 1959; 2.4
    This subseries consists of correspondence received by Flora Whitney Miller and the Whitney Museum of American Art after the death of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney. Included are letters of condolence, and correspondence relating to the Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney Estate, a memorial exhibition held at the Whitney Museum of American Art, gifts in memory of Whitney, and an exhibition of Whitney sculpture at the Wilmington Society of Fine Arts in 1959.
    - Letters of Condolence to Flora Whitney Miller Upon the Death of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
    - Letters of Condolence to Juliana Force Upon the Death of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney Estate (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
      - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Flora Whitney Miller Correspondence Pertaining to Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1947-1959 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Journals, circa 1886-1939; Series 3; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 9-12, 33
  This series consists of journals, diaries, and notebooks kept by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney throughout her life and in which she documented personal thoughts and experiences, and social events and happenings in her life.
  Journals have been scanned in entirety.
  Journals are arranged as two chronological subseries.
  3.1: Personal Journals, circa 1886-1939
  3.2: Social Journals, 1893-1920
  - Personal Journals, circa 1886-1939; 3.1
    This subseries consists of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's journals of a more personal nature. Personal journals range from ones she kept as a child and adolescent to ones she kept during her engagement and honeymoon to ones she kept as an adult, and include travel journals, impression books, diaries, confessions album, writing journals, and "A Line A Day" books. Personal journals record Whitney's trips abroad and time spent in Newport as a young girl, her impressions of people, her experiences with friends, her honeymoon trip to Japan, certain early writing efforts, her "thoughts relating to art, subjects for statues, composition symbols, all manner of substances which affects [her] artistic life" (from Art Journal, 1906-1907), her work with the Juilly Hospital in France during the First World War, trips to Spain in 1920 and 1928-1929, and daily events and impressions for certain periods of time.
    Personal journals are arranged chronologically.